Welcome back. In this lesson, we're unlocking one of TypeScript's superpowers, which is
generics. generics lets us write a reasonable code that works with many types, while still
keeping everything type safe. We're going to learn how to create generic functions, types
and components that adapt to whatever data we throw at them. So what exactly is a generic?
Well, a generic is a placeholder for a type. So instead of hard coding a specific type,
we use a variable, which in usual, usual case is t. And that gets filled in when the function
or the type is used. So let me just show you an example. So let's create a function and
a function, perhaps we're going to call it identity. And we want a value. We want to give
it a type. Now, our identity could be perhaps a string or it could be a number. So what
we want to do is we can do a less than sign here. And then a greater than sign. And we
want the variable t in here. So this becomes the generic as this, a generic type here. And
for our value, we also want to let it be a generic, which means we're not going to decide
an advance what type it's going to be. So we're going to have a code on and then give it
that variable t. And lastly, we want to return an actual value to the caller, but we also
want it to be a generic, which means we don't want it to determine at one time what the
type's going to be. So we do a colon and also variable t. And then we write the body or
the function, which we can just say return a value. So it looks a little bit strange, but
let's now work out how you can call this function. So we could say identity. And the value
as a certain TypeScript is currently unknown. It will be supplied when we actually call
the function. So let's say we call the function with a string. And now TypeScript
knows that we are actually providing a value of a string or a type of halo as a string
to our function. Let's now call the function again, and we say identity, and we're going
to provide a number. So now is the terms that we are providing a number as a value, a
value of 42. So this function works with any type, and TypeScript keeps track of what
t is each time. But why not use a way of using the or in the alternative type in TypeScript?
Why can't we say, for example, a string or it could be a number? Well, in that way we're
just restricting what types we are actually allowing to our function. We are only allowing
strings and integers. But maybe at run time we don't want to just allow strings and numbers,
but we also want to have maybe floating points or provide an object. And we don't really
know the shape of that object. And that's where generics come in is a particular advantage,
because we can just say, we don't know, and we don't care during compile time what the
actual function is. Basically, well, we're actually writing the code, but when we actually
call the code, then TypeScript's going to know at that point what the function or the
type is. You might ask a question, why don't we just have like an alternative type
so we have like a string and then we say, or it's a number. Well, if we do that way, then
we are restricting ourselves to just those two types, the ones we specify. But we want
to have a ability to pass like any shape object to a function. And then we want to use generics
because then TypeScript's going to handle what the type is going to be. So generics
is going to give us reusability. So we write one function and for many different types.
But it's also still allowing us to have type safety because TypeScript still is going to
be checking everything for us. And also provides clarity because we document our intent
without repeating code. So let's just do another kind of example little bit space on what
we did here. Let's have a function where we want to wrap a value in array, simply take
a value and then we want to put it into an array. So our function could be wrap in array.
We're going to provide a generic type t here and a value of type t. And the return type
is going to be an array. So how do we do that? Well, we say it's going to return a type
of a t, but it's an array. So take our t and we put two brackets, two square brackets
and it's rather than, for example, an array of strings or array of a number or a Boolean,
for example, we just put t because it's unknown at that point. We can then write our function
and all we want to do is take our value and put it inside an array. And now we can call
our function wrap in array and you can provide a string and it's then going to provide
we're going to return an array with Apple in it. Or we can call wrap in array and say,
for example, 99. And that's going to return an array with 99 in it. So let's now work
on a little bit more, more complex and actually have a generic type alias where it could
be a little bit more useful. So just imagine you want to have a response from an API,
but you don't actually know what that shape of that response is. All you're going to want
to have is the data for the response and an error message as a string. So we could have
a type of API response. And we don't know what the actual specifics of the data. So we're
going to say it's unknown. And then we're going to provide our data property of a type
of unknown. But what we think we do know is that we're going to have an error, optional
error, where we are going to have a string. So now you can see this data could take in many
forms. I would depending on whatever API response we're currently getting. So we can now
have, for example, a response of a user response coming from an API. So that is of type
API response. And then we specify the actual shape of that response when we actually
utilize it. So inside Square brackets, we're now defining what T actually is. So in this case T is
an object where we have a name and we have a string property. Then we finish off our list
and sign. So we're basically again providing just the shape of the T in this bit is just
here. And now we have an equal sign. And we can set up the data. Now we specify what that
data is. So we can see the name is Alice. Now if you don't do it to provide that information.
So if we come in here and we say it seems to come on to brackets, it's going to underline
it because it's expecting us to provide that shape. So TypeScript has now looked at the type
that we've provided here and it's now enforcing us to provide that type, all that property
of type name. So really this is where generics come as very
useful because it allows us to use generics and type aliases to model flexible structures
like API responses, form states or perhaps component properties. So let's just work
on another example. And this we're going to create a generic interface of type box.
So we could have an interface. And it's a box with a generic type. And that box is going
to have a property called content with a generic type. And now what we can do is we can have
a few different boxes. We could have a string box. The box is going to be of type string.
And then we're going to provide the content and the content is going to have the word
hello in it. And now we could have another type of box. We could call it a number
box. Box this time is a number. So t type t is now a number. And our content, this time
is not a string but a number. So interfaces work very much like type aliases. And they're
great for reusable objects shapes. We could also restrict what types are allowed using
extends. So for example, let's create another function. And we're going to call it print
length. This is going to be of type t. But we want to restrict the types are allowed. So
this is where I spoke about if you want to maybe have a string and a number only or certain
things, we can use the extends here. So we can say extends. And then we're going to provide
a length of number. And we are then going to provide our parameters. So this is item. And
item has a type of t which is going to be this restriction of hit just here. And our function
we want to not return anything. So if we don't want to return anything from our function,
let's say it returns void. And inside our actual function, I'm going to do a console log and
say item dot length. So again, our item is of type t. And our t is defined as having these
properties or this shape or having length and then a number. So now we can do print length. And if
we try and to print level string, we're going to get a length property on it. But it's going
to provide us with the length of the string. Of course, we could do print length again. And we
have, for example, one, two, three as an array. And the length property is going to interpret
that as an array and give us the length of array. We do print length. And we just say 42. Then
this doesn't actually have a length property. As you can see, so this is going to be thrown
out by TypeScript. So it's very useful using the extends when we need certain properties to
exist. If you know there's a length property on an array, or you know there's a length property
on a string, or you know there's a certain property on a certain object, then you can use
the extends in order to make sure that property exists. So generics basically lets us write
collectible, reusable code that adds apps to different types, whether it's losing type
safety. So if learns how to use generics and functions, types, and interfaces, and how to
constrain them when needed. Next up, we're going to be looking at map types when how to
transform types dynamically.